[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[2018, Beijing]
[2018년 베이징]
[Outside the 5th Ring Road of Beijing]
[5환 바깥 구역]
Sorry.
죄송합니다
It's clean.
깨끗한 물이에요
[Yuefu]
[웨푸]
I just got it filled from the tap.
방금 떠온 거예요
I'm sorry. I'm really sorry.
죄송합니다, 정말 죄송해요
It's okay.
괜찮아요
Isn't this Chen's shop?
여기 천 형 가게잖아?
Lu Yanchen?
루옌천?
Yes, him.
응, 맞아
Why? Are you close?
왜 그래? 잘 아는 사이야?
Kind of.
그럭저럭
I heard he's at the border.
국경 지대에 있다고 들었는데
He's back.
돌아와서
Is he doing this now?
지금 여기서 일해?
No.
그건 아냐
Chao.
차오
Has your boss's son come back?
사장님 아들 돌아왔어?
Yes.
돌아왔어요
He's at the gas station right by here.
바로 옆 주유소에 있어요
Okay, got it.
그래, 알겠어
Are you going?
갈래?
Do you...
당신
still remember who I am?
나 누군지 기억해?
Yes.
기억해
I'll remember you even if you turn into ashes.
재가 되어도 난 널 기억해
[Road Home]
[귀로 : 너에게 돌아가는 길]
[Episode 1]
[제1화]
Why are you at the gas station?
천 형, 주유소에는 웬일이야?
Is there a mission?
임무라도 있어?
What mission can there be at the gas station?
주유소에 임무는 무슨
I'm waiting for someone.
누구 좀 기다리고 있어
Ask your brother to come look for me tonight.
저녁에 너희 형더러 나 찾아오라고 해
My brother is in Laogou,
형은 라오거우에 있어
I will tell him to look for you in a few days.
이틀 뒤에 오라고 할게
Never mind then.
그러면 됐어
I'm going back to Qi Ning in a few days.
난 이틀 후에 치닝으로 돌아가
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
I'm off.
갈게
Captain Lu, is she your ex-girlfriend?
대장님, 전 여친이에요?
No.
아니야
Hello?
여보세요?
Huang Ting. I'm Gui Xiao.
황팅, 나 구이샤오야
Gui Xiao?
구이샤오구나
I saw
오늘...
your cousin today.
너희 오빠 봤어
You saw my cousin?
우리 사촌 오빠를 봤다고?
Even my mom doesn't know he's back.
우리 엄마도 오빠가 돌아온 걸 모르는데
How did you meet him?
어떻게 만난 거야?
We met at the gas station this afternoon.
아까 주유소에서 우연히 만났어
He's with a few... colleagues, probably.
동료들이랑 같이 있는 것 같더라
We didn't talk much.
한 마디도 나누지 않았어
Do you...
너...
have his phone number?
오빠 전화번호 가지고 있어?
[11 years ago]
[11년 전]
Don't you think we're destined to meet?
우리 인연이 특별하다고 생각하지 않아?
How so?
왜 그렇게 생각해?
Look.
봐봐
The last word
오빠 이름의
of your name is Chen.
마지막 글자는 천이고
Mine is Xiao.
나는 샤오야
Chen Xiao.
천샤오
That means the sunlight in the morning.
아침의 햇살이라는 뜻이잖아
Aren't we a match?
잘 어울리지?
Why didn't you drive?
왜 운전해서 오지 않았어?
It'd attract too much attention if I did.
차를 가져오면 너무 시선을 끌어서
Did he leave?
갔어?
He left.
갔어
Chen.
천 형
Fortunately, no one saw us.
눈에 띄지 않아서 다행이다
Afraid of being seen?
누가 볼까 봐 걱정돼?
No.
아니
What's there to be afraid of?
걱정될 게 뭐 있어?
What are you thinking about?
무슨 생각을 하는 거야?
I've been talking for a long time.
한참 얘기했는데
But you haven't given me any response.
거들떠보지도 않네
I was thinking how you
네 옷이 왜 이렇게
wet your clothes.
젖었는지 생각하고 있었어
I told my aunt not to wash it.
고모한테 빨지 말라고 했는데
She didn't listen to me and still washed it.
내 말을 듣지 않고 세탁하셨어
You're wearing clothes that hasn't dried yet,
마르지도 않은 옷을 입고
don't you find it cold?
춥지 않아?
I just bought this.
새로 산 옷인데
I wanted to wear it for you.
오빠한테 보여주고 싶었단 말이야
What's wrong? It doesn't look good?
왜? 안 예뻐?
It's not bad.
괜찮네
Not bad...
괜찮다니
I'm freezing and I only get a "not bad."
얼어 죽겠는데 괜찮다는 한마디가 다야?
You haven't praised me before.
아직 나한테 칭찬 안 해줬어
Say I'm pretty.
예쁘다고 해
Come on, praise me.
빨리 예쁘다고 칭찬하라니까?
Hurry up. Praise me.
빨리 예쁘다고 칭찬해줘
[2018]
[2018년]
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Why look for him?
왜 아직도 루천 오빠를 찾는 거야?
He begged
애초에 오빠가 너한테
to make up with you so many times back then.
몇 번이나 화해하자고 빌었는지 다 잊었어?
Do you know how cruel you were?
네가 그때 얼마나 모질었는지 알아?
It was a rare chance that he could return
모처럼 돌아와서
but you refused to see him.
널 만나고 싶어 했는데 네가 거절했잖아
But I'll send you the phone number.
그래도 번호는 보내줄게
It's up to you whether you call or not.
전화를 걸지 말지는 네가 알아서 해
I think it's been more than eight years.
이미 8년이나 지났으니
There's no need to contact each other anymore.
굳이 연락할 필요 없을 것 같아
Hello?
여보세요
Cousin.
오빠
It's me, Huang Ting.
나야, 황팅
You're back?
돌아왔어?
I'm on leave. There happens to be something I have to take care of too.
휴가야, 볼일도 볼 겸
Are you coming over for dinner then?
그럼 집에 와서 밥 먹을래?
My mom asked you to come.
엄마가 오빠더러 오라고 하셨어
I shan't.
아니야
I'm leaving by train tomorrow.
내일 기차로 돌아가
Cousin.
오빠
Go ahead.
할 말 있으면 해
Did you run into Gui Xiao
아까 주유소에서
at the gas station this afternoon?
구이샤오 만났어?
She asked me
방금 나한테
for your phone number.
오빠 전화번호를 알려달라고 하던데
I don't know if she'll call you.
연락할지 안 할지 모르겠네
Got it.
그래
♫Waiting to meet someone♫
♫ 누군가를 만나길 기다리는 건 ♫
♫Who can know how to savor♫
♫ 자세히 음미할 수 있는 일이지 ♫
♫On a night with wine and wind♫
♫ 술도 바람도 부는 어느 밤의 ♫
What are you doing here
이 밤중에 안 자고
not sleeping in the middle of the night?
여기서 뭐 하니?
I'm seeing if the grapes are ripe.
포도가 익었는지 보고 있어요
These grapes don't taste good.
그 포도는 정말 맛없어
They're sour.
너무 셔
♫Half a moon♫
♫ 반쪽짜리 달빛 ♫
If you want grapes,
먹고 싶으면
I'll buy some for you tomorrow.
내일 사다 줄게
I like sour ones like this.
저는 이 신 포도가 좋아요
♫Moon♫
♫ 달빛 ♫
This kid.
얘도 참
♫You must have wiped it silently♫
♫ 그대는 분명 오랜 시간을 ♫
♫For a long time♫
♫ 묵묵히 닦아냈겠지 ♫
♫Knowing that life is silent♫
♫ 삶이 수수께끼처럼 고요할 때 ♫
♫Only have the light when it's like a mystery♫
♫ 비로소 빛이 난다는 걸 잘 알고 있어 ♫
♫On a night when no one knows♫
♫ 아무도 모르는 밤 ♫
♫The breeze goes everywhere♫
♫ 시원함이 가득하구나 ♫
♫The breeze♫
♫ 시원함이 ♫
♫You must have been there in secret♫
♫ 그대는 분명 가장 먼 곳을 ♫
♫To the farthest places♫
♫ 남몰래 가봤겠지 ♫
♫Bringing back the green plants of summer♫
♫ 한여름의 푸른 공기 ♫
♫And the fallen leaves of autumn♫
♫ 가을의 황금빛 들녘을 가지고 돌아왔어 ♫
[Two years later]
[2년 후]
♫On a night when you're dating in the garden♫
♫ 놀라서 꿈에서 깬 밤 ♫
[Qining City]
[치닝시]
♫The pathos of youth is sung♫
♫ 슬픈 청춘의 노래를 부르네 ♫
Use mine to call.
내 걸로 걸어봐
I got this number two years ago.
2년 전에 받은 번호인데
I don't know if it works.
걸어도 될지 모르겠어
Let's try it first.
일단 해보자
Hello, who is it?
여보세요, 누구십니까?
I'm Gui Xiao.
나 구이샤오야
Are you...
지금...
busy?
바빠?
No.
아니
Go ahead.
말해
I'm in Qining,
나 지금 치닝으로
on a business trip.
출장 왔는데
I ran into some trouble.
곤란한 일이 생겼거든
I lost my car.
차를 잃어버렸어
Address.
주소
Send me the address.
문자로 주소 보내줘
Okay, I'll send it to you right away.
응, 바로 보낼게
Why aren't you going up?
왜 안 타고 있어?
Get in.
타
I'll take you there first.
먼저 너를 데려다줄게
I need to meet someone.
나는 만나러 갈 사람이 있어
Okay.
그래
Can your friend really come?
그 친구는 정말 올 수 있어?
Probably.
그럴 거야
How about
아니면
we make another call?
다시 전화 걸어 보자
Let's not.
아니야
What if he's on a mission?
임무 수행 중일 수도 있는데
It's not good to keep calling him.
또 걸면 귀찮게 하는 거잖아
If he doesn't come, then let's just forget it.
오지 않으면 어쩔 수 없지
We'll call the police.
경찰에 신고하자
Let's wait inside.
들어가서 기다리자
You go in first.
먼저 들어가 있어
My back hurts from sitting inside.
안에 앉아 있으니 허리가 아파서
Let me get some fresh air.
바람 쐬러 나왔어
Okay, I'm going in.
그래, 나 들어갈게
♫Can you hear me?♫
♫ 들리나요 ♫
♫All these years♫
♫ 오랜 세월 ♫
♫The anticipation from the depths of my soul♫
♫ 내 영혼 깊은 곳에서 온 기대 ♫
Get in.
차에 타
♫An ethereal heart♫
♫ 공허한 마음 ♫
The owner of the gas station told us
주유소 사장님께서
to check the prairie first.
일단 초원에 가보라고 하셨어
♫A healed wound♫
♫다 나은 상처 ♫
We might be able to find the car.
차를 바로 찾을 수 있을지도 몰라
♫The eagerness to wait for you has overtaken the anxiety♫
♫ 당신의 마음을 기다리며 불안함을 떨쳐요 ♫
Get in.
차에 타
I have three friends with me too.
친구 세 명이 더 있어
I'll go get them,
가서 불러올게
give me a while.
잠시만
Let's go.
서둘러, 가자
He's here.
왔어
Finally.
드디어 왔구나
We got some help.
살았다
Nice to meet you, Captain Lu.
루 대장님, 만나서 반가워요
We'll sit behind.
우리는 뒤에 타자
Okay.
그래, 그러자
He's still the same.
예전이랑 똑같네
Regardless of if it's spring, summer, autumn, or winter,
어느 계절이든 간에
he has to have the window opened.
늘 차창을 열어두고 있어
Can you close the window?
창문 좀 닫아줄래?
Gui Xiao's friend is so cool.
구이샤오 친구 카리스마 넘친다
He's a SWAT captain.
경찰특공대 대대장이라잖아
Of course he's cool. How else can he scare the criminals
카리스마가 없으면 어떻게 범죄자를 겁주고
and protect us?
우리를 지켜주겠어?
We lost our car
두 시간 전에
two hours ago.
차를 잃어버렸어
I wanted to call the police,
경찰에 신고하려고 했는데
but thought of you,
네 생각이 나서
so I called to ask.
전화를 걸어 물어본 거야
The owner of the gas station said
주유소 사장님께서
given his experience,
본인의 경험으로는
the car is likely to be
아마도 차가
in a forest not far away.
멀지 않은 숲속에 있을 거라고 하셨어
The car thieves
그 차 도둑들은
have nowhere to park the cars they've looted from
지나가던 차를 훔치고 둘 곳이 없어서
so they'd toss them there.
모두 거기에 버린대
These thieves are so smart.
그 도둑들 똑똑하지 않아?
There are no cameras there.
거기에는 감시 카메라가 없으니
Even if we find the car,
차를 찾는다고 해도
we won't be able to find out who stole it.
누가 훔쳤는지 알 수 없잖아
Captain Lu, do you know the way?
루 대장님, 가는 길 아세요?
Yes.
압니다
That's good.
아신다니 다행이네요
We'll follow you then.
그럼 저희는 따라가면 되겠어요
It's snowy.
눈이 많이 내리니
Drive slowly.
천천히 운전하세요
I called the police for you.
제가 경찰에 신고하겠습니다
The person in charge will be here soon.
이따 담당자가 올 겁니다
Your friend is so cold.
네 친구 너무 무뚝뚝하다
I was too scared to
감히 고맙다는 말도
say thank you to him.
못 할 정도로 무섭네
He's always been like this.
항상 저랬어
I'll go down
내려서
and talk to him.
얘기 좀 할게
Slowly.
다녀와
Aren't you cold?
안 추워?
This is yours.
이 차가 네 거야
Thank you.
고마워
For helping me.
도와줘서
You're welcome.
아니야
How long have you been here?
여기에 있은 지 얼마나 됐어?
Nine years.
9년
You haven't been promoted yet?
아직 승진하지는 않았어?
I have.
이미 했어
Are you going back?
돌아갈 거야?
Since you've been promoted,
승진하면
you can apply to be transferred back, right?
전근 신청할 수 있는 거 아니야?
I'm not going back.
안 돌아가
I'm staying here.
여기에 있을 거야
What brings you here?
왜 갑자기 온 거야?
The girl in the car
차에 타고 있는 친구가
does international trade.
무역 일을 해
She came here for business.
사업 때문에 왔는데
So I came here for a trip.
나는 따라서 여행하러 왔어
It's so snowy
눈보라 치는 날에
and you're here for a trip?
여행을 왔어?
Snow is also a specialty here.
눈보라도 이곳의 특색이잖아
Captain Lu.
루 대장
This is the person who called the police.
이분이 신고한 분입니다
I'll leave it to you.
맡아주시죠
This is her car.
이 차가 이분의 것이고
And these cars
다른 차들도
were also stolen.
도난당한 겁니다
These stolen cars already have a police report lodged.
이 차들은 이미 신고된 차들이고
The thieves have been apprehended
차 도둑들은 다 잡았어요
but they refused to tell us
여태껏 차를 숨긴 곳을
where the stolen cars were hidden.
자백하지 않았는데
Turns out they were hidden here.
이제 보니 여기에 숨겨뒀었군요
I found it by chance.
우연히 찾았습니다
I'll leave it to you.
그럼 부탁드립니다
- I’ve got something else on. I’m leaving. - Okay, go ahead.
- 일이 있어서 먼저 가보겠습니다 - 네, 가봐요
Hello, I'm the car owner.
안녕하세요, 제가 차 주인이에요
Okay.
네
If it's convenient,
괜찮으시다면
could you drive back
차를 몰고 저와 함께
with me
돌아가셔서
to take a statement?
진술서를 작성해 주시죠
Sure.
네, 그럴게요
Okay.
좋습니다
Thank you.
감사합니다
You're welcome.
아닙니다
Where are you going next?
이제 어디로 가십니까?
We want to stay in town for a few days
일단 마을에서 며칠 머물고
and then go to Qining City.
치닝시를 둘러보려고 해요
Business first, then travel.
비즈니스부터 하고 여행하려고요
Are you close to that
아까 그 루 대장님과
Captain Lu just now?
잘 아는 사이세요?
We've known each other for years.
안 지 오래됐죠
But we only meet
그런데 1년에
a few times a year.
몇 번 못 봅니다
He's in Qining City.
루 대장은 치닝 시내에
He doesn't come here often.
자주 나오지 않거든요
He's a nice guy.
아주 괜찮은 젊은이에요
He's always on the frontline of the SWAT.
늘 경찰특공대의 최전선에 있어요
It must be tiring to be on the frontline.
최전선은 힘들죠?
Of course.
그럼요
It's also very dangerous.
게다가 아주 위험합니다
But he’s an instructor now.
그런데 이제 교관이 돼서
He teaches others how to detonate bombs.
폭발물 처리까지 가르치고 있어요
When he is on a mission,
임무가 있을 때는
he would be on the frontline of counterterrorism.
대테러의 일선에 있고
He has
평소에는
trained many heroes
훌륭한 부하들을 데리고 나와서
to protect the people.
시민들을 지키는
A real man.
진짜 사나이죠
Bomb detonation?
폭발물 처리요?
He's a bomb detonation expert?
폭발물 처리 담당이에요?
Yes.
네
Their team
루 대장의 모든 대대가
is the counterterrorism team.
대테러의 선봉이에요
There were dozens of experts
폭발물 처리팀에서
that came out of the bomb detonation team.
수십 명의 전문가가 먼저 나와
They were all poached internally.
내부를 처리하죠
Captain Lu
루 대장은
could detonate a ticking bomb in 30 seconds
30초 시한폭탄을 해체하는데
without even breaking a sweat.
땀 한 방울도 흘리지 않았어요
This is not a movie.
이건 영화가 아니라
It really happened.
진짜 있었던 일입니다
You're here to fix the roof?
지붕 수리하러 왔어요?
Be careful.
조심해요
Lu!
옌천!
The old captain's father
대장 댁 어르신께서
is waiting for you.
기다리고 계셔!
What's wrong?
왜 그래?
You came all the way here
한숨 돌리려고
to get some fresh air?
여기까지 달려온 거야?
I wanted to visit the old captain's father first.
먼저 어르신을 뵈러 가려고 했는데
But I thought about it
생각해 보니
and decided not to.
됐다 싶었어
You have no idea
너는 그 사람들이
how they made me cry.
나를 울리는 것도 모르지?
You can cry in front of me,
내 앞에서는 울어도 되는데
but don't cry at their place.
그 사람들 집에서는 울지 마
I understand.
알겠어
We can't use these planks anymore.
이 판자들은 쓸 수 없어
Pass me the toolbox
차에 있는 공구함과
and the boards we brought
우리가 가져온 판자를
from the car.
가져다줘
I'll fix the opening gap first.
먼저 갈라진 곳부터 메우자
Otherwise, with this heavy snow,
안 그러면 이렇게 눈이 많이 오는 날에
the things in it
밑에 놓여 있는 것들이
will get wet when the snow melts.
눈 녹을 때 다 젖을 거야
Okay, we have work to do again.
그래, 또 할 일이 생겼네
Be careful.
조심히 해
Thank you.
고맙네
This is from me personally.
이건 제가 개인적으로 드리는 겁니다
No, no.
됐네, 됐어
Uncle,
아저씨
I've been in Qining for so many years.
제가 치닝에 오고 나서 여러 해 동안
I've been taken care of by your family.
아저씨께서 많이 보살펴주셨잖아요
Chinese New Year is coming.
곧 새해이니
Take it as some sincerity by me,
반쪽짜리 아들이
who take you as dear as my father.
효도한다고 생각하세요
He doesn't spend much.
평소에 돈도 잘 안 쓰고
He also saved a lot.
모은 것도 꽤 있어
He's not even here anymore.
사람도 없고 말이야
Chen, I really don't need it.
옌천, 이 돈은 정말 필요 없어
Don't take it to heart.
여기 일은 너무 마음에 두지 마
I still have to count on you
앞으로 네가 치닝에 있으면
in Qining.
네가 잘 보살펴 드려
Of course. I don't need you to remind me.
무슨 소리야, 네가 알려줘야지
I'll go back to the team later. What about you?
나는 이따가 부대로 돌아갈 거야, 너는?
Oh right,
참
you have to pick up Nan for me.
너는 나 대신 샤오난 데리러 가야 해
Have you asked Captain Lu yet?
루 대장님이랑 약속 잡았어?
No.
아니
I'm treating.
내가 살 거야
I asked you to ask them out,
너한테 약속 잡으라고 하는 거지
not to pay.
돈 내라고 하는 거 아니야
I don't want to ask him out no matter how much money it is.
돈을 얼마나 쓰든 만나고 싶지 않아
How can you be so cruel?
왜 이렇게 모질게 굴어?
It snowed so heavily yesterday.
어제 눈이 그렇게 많이 오는데
He came to help you.
친히 와서 도와줬잖아
And I'm not the only one.
그리고 나뿐만 아니라
Zhou and Lin Yao
다들
want to treat him to dinner too.
루 대장님한테 대접하고 싶어 해
He didn't like socialising.
예전에는 접대하는 자리를 좋아하지 않았어
It's not socialising. It's just a meal to say thanks.
접대가 아니라 감사의 의미지
We just admire heroes.
은인을 단순하게 대해서는 안 돼
I have his number anyway.
어쨌든 나한테도 번호가 있어
Don't call him.
전화하지 마
No, I don't know him well.
아니, 나랑 안 친하다니까
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Why are you embarrassed?
어색할 게 뭐 있어?
You're being very immature.
정말 철이 안 들었네
He helped you so much.
너를 그렇게 많이 도와줬는데...
He answered.
받았다
Hello?
여보세요
Hello, Captain Lu.
안녕하세요, 루 대장님
I'm Cai Yaya,
저 차이야야예요
Gui Xiao's friend.
어제 만났었던
We met yesterday.
구이샤오 친구예요
Hello.
안녕하세요
Yes.
참
Gui Xiao's phone didn't have any signal yesterday
어제 구이샤오 휴대전화 신호가 잡히지 않아서
so we called you with my phone.
제 휴대전화로 걸었었어요
Please don't mind that
너무 신경쓰지 마세요
I've saved your number.
제가 그냥 저장한 거예요
It's okay.
괜찮습니다
Did something happen?
무슨 문제라도 있으십니까?
No.
아무 문제 없어요
I just want to treat you to a meal
감사의 의미로
to express my gratitude.
한 끼 대접하고 싶어서요
You have no idea how important
이 차가 저에게 얼마나
this car is to me.
중요한지 모르실 거예요
My husband just gave it to me.
얼마 전에 남편이 선물해 준 건데
If I lose it, it would bring a huge crisis to my family.
잃어버렸으면 큰일 날 뻔했어요
Thank you so much.
정말 감사해요
Let's not delay it. How about tonight?
미루지 말고 오늘 저녁으로 하죠
Okay.
네, 그래요
I'll send you
제가 이따가 식당 주소를
the restaurant address later.
보내드릴게요
Okay.
좋아요
Get changed.
옷 갈아입어
Let's go eat.
밥 먹으러 가자
Close the door.
문 닫아
Your awareness is amazing.
반정찰 능력이 너무 뛰어나요
You call this awareness?
이걸 반정찰이라고 한다면
That's nothing.
나를 너무 얕봤네
You're going home?
집에 가요?
Going for dinner.
밥 먹을 거야
With whom?
누구랑요?
An old friend.
옛 친구랑
You have friends
동료 말고
besides colleagues?
친구도 있어요?
You've grown taller.
또 컸네
You are half a head taller
친구들보다
than your classmates.
머리 하나가 더 빨리 자랐어
Of course.
그럼요
Fasten your seat belt.
안전벨트 매
This is it.
이 방입니다
Whose child is this?
이 아이는 누구인가요?
Tell their parents,
보호자한테 알려주세요
if not they might get worried that their kid went to the wrong room.
아이가 길을 잃으면 부모님이 걱정하겠어요
Auntie, I’m with Lu Yanchen.
아주머니, 저희 아빠는 루옌천이에요
My dad went to make a call.
아빠는 전화하러 가셨고
He asked me to wait for the guests here.
저는 여기에 남아 손님을 기다리라고 하셨어요
I need to use the bathroom.
화장실 좀 다녀올게
Auntie, go out and turn right.
아주머니, 화장실은 나가서 오른쪽으로 돌아
The toilet is right at the end.
복도 끝까지 가시면 돼요
Uncles, auntie, please sit down.
아주머니, 아저씨, 앉으세요
This kid is so sensible.
애가 아주 의젓하네
My dad taught me well.
아빠가 잘 가르치셨거든요
We broke up ten years ago.
10년 전에 헤어졌으니
This child is so big.
아이가 이렇게 큰 것도
It makes sense.
일리가 있네
He said he would stay here in the future,
앞으로도 여기에 머무를 거라고 한 건
which means he has a home here.
가정이 생겼다는 뜻이었어
Everything makes sense.
모든 게 경우에 들어맞아
So, Gui Xiao,
그러니까 구이샤오
why are you still looking for him?
넌 그 사람을 찾아서 뭘 하려는 거야?
What are you looking at?
뭘 보고 있어?
The ladies' room is downstairs.
여자 화장실은 아래층이야
Come back.
돌아와
I'll take you there.
내가 데려다줄게
No need.
됐어
I asked you to come back, you hear me?
돌아오라니까, 안 들려?
Isn't it just because I dumped you back then?
애초에 널 찬 건 나잖아
You have a child now.
너는 아이도 있는데
Why are you still acting like I owe you?
아직도 내가 너한테 빚진 것처럼
What are you doing?
굴 거 없잖아?
I didn't hear you.
못 들었어
You didn't hear me?
못 들었다면서
Then why are you turning back?
고개는 왜 돌려?
She
아가씨가
doesn't want to talk to you.
너랑 상대하기 싫어하시잖아
Please forgive him, Miss.
너무 언짢아하지 마세요
Captain Lu is...
우리 루 대장이, 아니지
I mean, the former captain,
전 대대장이
he just submitted his resignation report.
사직서를 제출한 지 며칠 안 됐는데
He has nothing better to do.
너무 한가해서 그런지
Acting all weird.
이상하게 굴거든요
Didn't you say...
전에 말할 땐...
I'm unemployed now.
지금 난 백수야
Why?
왜?
You think it's not worth buying me a meal now?
밥 사주는 게 아까워?
Miss, don't be too offended.
아가씨, 너무 이상하게 생각하지 마세요
Captain Lu is very straightforward with his words.
우리 루 대장이 말을 좀 매섭게 해요
I know.
알아요
Actually, Captain Lu
사실 루 대장이
is still hesitating
지금도 베이징으로
whether he should go back to Beijing or not.
돌아갈지 말지
He's hesitating.
망설이고 있어요
He's not exactly unemployed.
백수라고 하기에는
It's just temporary unemployment.
기껏해야 단기 실업인 거잖아
I might not necessarily go back.
안 돌아갈 수도 있어
It's quite troublesome to return to Beijing
아내와 아이를 데리고 베이징으로 돌아가는 건
if you have to bring your wife and kid along.
번거로운 일이겠네
Household registration would be troublesome too.
호적 등록도 성가실 텐데
If you need
만약에 도움이
any help,
필요한 게 있으면
you can look for me.
나한테 연락해
Looks like your son is up to something again.
네 아들이 또 장난을 쳤나 보네
No way.
그럴 리가
He's so afraid of you.
너를 그렇게 무서워하는데
How could he play tricks on you?
어떻게 너한테 장난을 쳤겠어?
But it's possible too.
아마도
He's grown up
요즘에 많이 커서
and is bolder now.
대담해졌나 봐
Miss, here's the thing.
그게 말이죠
Miss, please forgive me.
이상하게 생각하지 마세요
That is my son.
그 아이는 제 아들이에요
My son
제 아들이
knows there are many bachelors in the team.
우리 대대에 미혼인 친구들이 많으니까
When they go on blind dates,
대원들이 맞선을 볼 때면
he'd pull some tricks.
못된 장난을 쳐요
He kept calling them his father,
이 사람 저 사람한테 아빠라고 불러서
chasing away many ladies.
많은 여성분이 도망갔어요
I apologize.
죄송합니다
So that's not your son.
네 아들이 아니야?
What a pity.
안타깝네
He's so cute.
아주 귀엽던데
He's cute?
귀엽다고요?
That brat is up to no good.
그 녀석은 귀신도 도망갈 겁니다
Oh right,
참
let me introduce myself.
제 소개를 하죠
My name is Qin Mingyu.
저는 친밍위라고 합니다
I'm from Lu Yanchen's team.
루 대장의 대대에 있습니다
That brat is my son.
그 장난꾸러기 녀석은 제 아들이고
His name is Qin Xiaonan.
이름은 친샤오난이에요
I'm Gui Xiao.
저는 구이샤오예요
Weren't you going to the toilet?
화장실 가려던 거 아니었어?
I don't want to go anymore.
갑자기 안 가고 싶어졌어
Dad.
아빠
Hello.
안녕하십니까
You played tricks again.
이 녀석, 또 장난쳤지?
Dang, we all got it wrong.
네, 제가 다 잘못했어요
Here.
자
Apologize to Auntie Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모한테 사과드려
Auntie, I was wrong.
이모, 제가 잘못했어요
It's okay.
아냐, 괜찮아
Don't stand around. Sit down.
서 있지 말고 어서 앉으세요
Sit.
앉아
Captain Lu, please have a seat.
루 대장님, 앉으세요
I don’t know much
제가 이 식당을
about the restaurants here.
잘 모르기는 하는데
I picked this place based on its reviews.
후기를 보고 골랐어요
As to the dishes,
음식은
I'll ask the waiter to serve the signature dishes.
이 집의 대표 메뉴를 가져다 달라고 했고요
Is that okay?
괜찮으시죠?
Captain Lu, is there anything you don't eat?
루 대장님, 가리는 음식 있으세요?
He eats anything.
없어
No.
없습니다
Okay.
그렇군요
Please enjoy.
맛있게 드세요
Captain Lu,
루 대장님
were you neighbors
구이샤오랑
or schoolmates
예전에 이웃이셨어요?
with Gui Xiao?
아니면 동창이셨나요?
Schoolmates.
동창입니다
We're not close.
친하지는 않습니다
Qining's snow is so heavy.
치닝은 눈이 정말 많이 오네요
Captain Lu
우리 루 대장이
is not good at talking.
말주변이 없는 편이에요
We've sat here for a while now
보세요, 여기 앉아서
but he hasn't talked much.
몇 마디도 하지 않았잖아요
But Captain Lu
그런데 루 대장은
is someone who's cold on the outside but warm on the inside.
겉은 차갑고 속은 따뜻한 사람이에요
He must treat you
분명히 여러분을
as friends,
친구로 여겨서
that's why he's here.
이 자리에 왔을 겁니다
Right, Captain Lu?
안 그래, 루 대장?
Schoolmates right? Chat a little.
동창이잖아, 얘기 좀 해
Have a drink.
한 잔 드려
- Drink your own. - Captain Lu has to drive.
- 네 거나 마셔 - 루 대장은 운전해야 하니...
Exactly, dad.
아빠
Eat your food.
식사하세요
I was thinking
루 대장이 곧 베이징으로
Captain Lu's going to Beijing soon.
가니까 말씀드리는 겁니다
Please take care of him.
친구분들께서 좀 잘 챙겨주세요
If you can't say it yourself,
네가 말하기가 창피하면
I'll say it instead.
내가 할게
Here.
자
You have to drive later.
이따가 다들 운전하셔야 하니
Let's drink tea instead of wine.
술 대신에 차를 마시도록 하죠
I will drink a toast to everyone.
제가 한 잔 올리겠습니다
When you come to Qining in the future,
앞으로 치닝에 오셨을 때
if you have any problems,
어떤 문제라도 있으시면
just let me know, okay?
언제든지 말씀하세요
I hope
그리고
you can take care of Captain Lu
저를 대신해 베이징에서
in Beijing for me too.
우리 루 대장 좀 잘 보살펴 주시고요
Of course.
그럼요
We have to repay more than what we received.
은혜를 입으면 갑절로 갚아야 하는 법인데
Let alone Captain Lu has
루 대장님께서
helped us a lot.
이렇게 큰 도움을 주셨으니 당연히 그래야죠
We will help you in any way possible
나중에 저희가 도울 수 있는 건
in the future.
반드시 도울게요
Of course we'll help.
당연히 도와드려야죠
As long as Captain Lu asks, I'll be there at any time.
루 대장님께서 말씀만 하시면 언제든지요
Thank you, everyone.
다들 감사합니다
By the way, the four of you
참, 네 분께서
came here in one car, right?
차 한 대로 오신 건가요?
Yes.
네
Captain Lu, send them.
루 대장, 모셔다드려
Four people in a car
네 분이 차 한 대를 타면
is too crowded. It's not safe.
너무 좁겠다
Is it too troublesome?
너무 번거로우실 텐데요
No, auntie.
아니에요, 아주머니
We live in the west.
저희는 서쪽에 살고
And you live in the east.
아주머니와 아저씨는 동쪽에서 묵으셔서
Although it's not very convenient,
가는 길이 같지는 않지만
it shows
그래도 손님을 배웅하는
our sincerity by sending the guests off.
성의를 보여야 하잖아요
Captain Lu and I
그럼 저랑 루 대장님은
shall go get our cars from the parking lot.
일단 주차장에 가서 차를 가져올게요
You guys wait here.
너희는 여기서 기다려
Okay.
그래
Come with me.
너는 나랑 같이 가
Otherwise, I'll be frozen
루 대장님이랑 둘이 있다가는
to death by how cold he is.
어색해 죽을 거 같아
I'll wait for you here.
난 여기서 기다릴게
No, it's cold outside.
안 돼, 밖은 춥잖아
Come with me. Let's go.
나랑 같이 가, 가자
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
My car is over there.
제 차는 이쪽에 있어요
What about you?
루 대장님 차는요?
Over there.
저쪽이요
It's not far.
멀지 않네요
Don't come out.
나오지 마
Lu Chen!
루천!
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Are you okay?
너 괜찮아?
I was shoved a few times.
몇 번 밀렸는데
What are they doing?
저 사람들 뭐 하는 거야?
Watch out, Lu!
옌천, 조심해!
Dad.
아빠!
I already called the police
제가 아저씨 휴대전화로
with his phone.
경찰에 신고했어요!
Well done!
잘했어!
Are you scared?
무서웠어?
No.
아니
What is there to be scared of?
무섭기는
I covered you with my clothes
네가 놀랄까 봐
because I didn't want to scare you.
옷으로 덮어준 건데
I didn't expect you
눈치도 없이
to not take the hint at all
내 배려가 무색하게
and pulled it off,
옷을 내리고 다 지켜볼 줄을
watching it all the way.
생각지도 못했네
Here.
받아
Is there snow?
아직 눈이 있어?
No.
없어졌어
Captain Lu.
루 대장
We meet again.
또 만났네요
I'll leave them to you.
이자들을 넘기겠습니다
They're car thieves.
차 도둑들입니다
Okay.
그래요
Thank you.
감사합니다
I've got them to speak up.
알아봤어
They are friends
전에 잡힌
of the group of people who stole the cars.
차 도둑 일당의 친구들인데
They happen to be eating here.
이자들도 마침 여기서 밥을 먹다가
They recognized the car at first sight.
구이샤오 씨 차를 바로 알아보고
So they wanted to avenge
체포된 친구들을 대신해
for their friends.
화풀이하려고 했는데
But they didn't expect it's us who they'd face.
우리를 만날 줄을 몰랐던 거야
Chief Liu,
류 소장님
we captured
이번에
13 people for you,
13명을 잡아드렸으니
you should treat Captain Lu and me
저와 루 대장에게
to a big meal.
크게 한턱내셔야 합니다
Of course.
그럼요
Eat all you want at the police cafeteria.
경찰 구내식당에서 마음껏 드세요
Your car
여러분 차에
should be commended
우승기를 선물해야겠습니다
for saving our police force.
우리 경찰 자원을 아끼는 게
It also saved resources
국가의 자원을
for the country.
절약하는 일 아니겠습니까?
Sorry for the trouble.
실례가 많았어요
Not at all. I'm happy.
실례라니요, 아주 기쁜걸요
A kid reported the case just now.
방금 신고한 아이는
Who was it?
누군가요?
Me.
저예요
My son.
제 아들입니다
As usual.
규정에 따라...
We'll go back and make a statement with you.
함께 가서 조서를 작성하겠습니다
You drive Cai Yaya's car
네가 차이야야 씨 차를 운전해서
and send those two men back.
두 남성분을 모셔다드려
I'll drive them home.
내 차로 두 분을 모셔다드릴게
Okay.
그래
I'll go with Uncle Lu.
저는 옌천 삼촌이랑 갈래요
Now you know it's Uncle Lu?
이제 삼촌인 걸 알았네
[Establish a positive image for public security]
[공안 이미지를 확립합시다]
I don't mind
아빠라고 부르라고 하신다면
if you want me to call you dad.
기꺼이 그럴 수 있어요
W-why?
무, 무슨 소리야?
Can't I have two dads?
아빠가 둘인 건 안 되겠죠?
Thank you, Captain Qin.
친 대장님, 감사해요
Let's go.
가시죠
Auntie, don't be angry.
이모, 화내지 마세요
Uncle Lu has a cold face.
옌천 삼촌의 얼음장 같은 얼굴은
He treats everyone the same.
누구에게나 똑같아요
I'm not angry.
화 안 났어
I'm used to it.
예전부터 이미 익숙해